<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A briefe summe of Christian religion collected for a preparation to the Lords Supper / published for the benefit of the simpler sort of people of the parish of Saint Lawrence by Thomas Sanderson Doctor in Divinitie.</title>
            <author>Sanderson, Thomas, 1560 or 61-1614.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1640</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 15 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11459</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21710.7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S4880</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23996514</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23996514</idno>
            <idno type="VID">27070</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11459)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 27070)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1840:27)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A briefe summe of Christian religion collected for a preparation to the Lords Supper / published for the benefit of the simpler sort of people of the parish of Saint Lawrence by Thomas Sanderson Doctor in Divinitie.</title>
                  <author>Sanderson, Thomas, 1560 or 61-1614.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[15] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E.P. for F. Coules at his shop in the Old-Bayly neere the Sessions-house,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1640.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁸.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: tightly bound.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catechisms, English.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:27070:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27070:1"/>
            <p>A BRIEFE SUMME OF <hi>Chriſtian Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Collected for a preparation to the Lords Supper.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed for the benefit of</hi> the ſimpler ſort of people of the Pariſh of Saint <hi>Lawrence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BY THOMAS SANDERSON Doctor in Divinitie.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>PROV. 22.</bibl>
               <p>Teach a Child in the trade of his way, and when he is old he ſhall not depart from it.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>1 PET. 2.2.</bibl>
               <p>As new borne Babes deſire the ſincere milke of the Word, that yee may grow thereby.</p>
            </q>
            <p>London, Printed by <hi>E. P.</hi> for <hi>F. Coules,</hi> at his ſhop in the Old-Bayly, neere the Sesſions-houſe. 1640.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="catechism">
            <pb facs="tcp:27070:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27070:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>AN INTRODUCTION</hi> to the Lords Supper.</head>
            <p>
               <label>Queſtion.</label>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ho made you?<note place="margin">Gen. 1.1. &amp;c. Eſay. 66.2. Acts 17.24. Iohn 4.24. Iohn 1.18. 1 Tim. 6.16. Exod. 33.20. Iob 11.7. Eſay 40.12.13. &amp;c. Eſay 57.15. Rom. 1.20. Gen. 17.1. Iob 37.23. Eſay 54.5. Deut. 4.35. &amp; 6.4. Mat. 3.16.17. and 28.19. 1 Iohn 5.7. Pro. 16.4. Pſal. 104. and 145.146. and 148.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> GOD that made Man and all things in the beginning.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> What is God?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> A Spirit, Invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, Incomprehenſible, Infinite, Eternall, and Almightie, One in nature and ſubſtance, but diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed into thrée perſons, namely the Father, the Sonne, and the holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Why did God make all things?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> For his owne glory.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Why for his glory?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Becauſe he is moſt worthy to be glorified, that onely was and is able to give glory to all things.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:27070:3"/>
               <label>Q</label> How doth man glorifie God?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> By beléeving in him, and kéeping his Commandements.<note place="margin">Iohn 15.1.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> What is to be beléeved of God?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> The Articles of the Chriſtian Fath comprehended in the Apoſtles Créed, which is, I beléeve in God, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Which are Gods Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,<note place="margin">Exod. 20.1. Deut. 5.6.</note>
and how many be they?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Ten The ſame which GOD ſpake unto <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in the twentieth Chapter of <hi>Exodus,</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>I.</hi> I am the Lord thy God, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Can you kéepe theſe Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 2.9. Gal. 3.22.</note>
               <label>A.</label> I cannot.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> What is due unto them that doe not keepe Gods Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 25.26. Rom. 4.15. Deut. 23.22.</note>
               <label>A.</label> The Curſe of the Law, the wrath of God, and therefore the vengeance of eternall fire.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> How will you then eſcape theſe things?<note place="margin">Gal. 3.13. 1 Theſ. 1.10. Epheſ. 1.7. Acts 4.1.2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> By Ieſus Chriſt, mine onely Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer and Saviour.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:27070:3"/>
               <label>Q.</label> Why, what did Chriſt for you?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Hée dyed for my ſinnes, and roſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine for my juſtification.<note place="margin">Rom. 4.25.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> What is Chriſt?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> The Sonne of God.<note place="margin">Mat. 16.16. and 17.5. Luke 4.14. Heb. 1.5. 1 Pet. 3.18.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Why, how could the Sonne of God ſuffer death?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Hee ſuffred in his Man-hood: for hee is both God and Man in one perſon.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> How can that be?<note place="margin">Rom. 1.3.4. Phil. 2.6, 7.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Yes very well: for as the bodie and the ſoule doe make but one Man: ſo God and man are but one Chriſt.<note place="margin">A<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hanaſ. Symb.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> How doe you know that Chriſt dyed and roſe againe for you?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> By Faith, becauſe I verily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeve it.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Whence commeth faith?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> It is the gift and worke of God,<note place="margin">Phil. 1.29. Iohn 6.29.</note> wrought in my heart by the Holy Ghoſt, who ſanctifieth me and all GODS choſen Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.<note place="margin">Iohn 12.13. Rom. 8.11. 1 Cor. 6.11. 2 Theſ. 2.13.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> By what meanes doth the Holy Ghoſt worke faith in you?</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:27070:4"/>
               <label>A.</label> By the Word of GOD, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Old Teſtament and the New.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> How by the Word of God?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Ioſu. 2.8. Iob 5.19. Acts 17.11. Eſay 1.2.</note>
               <label>A.</label> By reading and meditating, and conferring upon it: But moſt eſpecially by hearing it preached and expounded unto me: as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith in the tenth Chapter to the <hi>Romans: <q>Faith commeth by hearing, and hearing by the Word of God.</q>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 10.17.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> How is Faith ſtrengthned and encreaſed?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> By the ſame Word, and by the Sacraments.<note place="margin">Acts 2.42.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Q</label> What is a Sacrament?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> It is an outward ſigne ordained by Chriſt, to ſignifie an inward and inviſible Grace.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> How many Sacraments be there?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 11.12. Iohn 5.6. 1 Cor. 11.23. Mat. 28.16. Acts 8.38. &amp; 10.47.</note>
               <label>A.</label> Two: Baptiſme, and the Lords Supper.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> What is Baptiſme?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> It is both an eternall or out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward waſhing of the body with wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: and alſo an inward and ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
<pb facs="tcp:27070:4"/>
waſhing of our ſoules and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies from ſinne in the blood-ſhed and merits of our Lord IESVS Chriſt.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 12.13. Epheſ. 5.26. Titus 3.5.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> So then the ſigne in Baptiſme is Water: and the inviſible Grace, is Regeneration or New birth, which we have of Ieſus Chriſt. Is it not ſo?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> It is ſo. For by Ieſus Chriſt wee have both remiſſion of our ſins, and Sanctification from them,<note place="margin">Col. 1.14. 1 Iohn 1.7. 1 Cor. 1.30.</note> and that is Regeneration or New-birth.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> What is the Lords Supper?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> It is the repreſentation of his death and paſſion, under the viſible ſignes of Bread and VVine.<note place="margin">Luke 22.19. 1 Cor. 11.24.25.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Why is it called the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Becauſe it was ordained by the Lord immediately after Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, as a ſecond banquet or ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Supper:<note place="margin">Luke 22.29. 1 Cor. 11.25.</note> For as our bodies doe feed upon naturall food: So our ſoules and bodies both are ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually nouriſhed with the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all <hi>Manna</hi> that came downe from
<pb facs="tcp:27070:5"/>
heaven, which is our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.<note place="margin">Iohn 6.41. 1 Cor. 10.3.4.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> What is then received by you in this Supper?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Outwardly by the Mouth, Bread and Wine: But inwardly by faith in my heart,<note place="margin">Mat. 26.2. 1 Cor. 10.21. Verſe 16.</note> the Body and Blood of Chriſt: and therefore it is alſo called the Lords Table, and the holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> How can you doe this?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 26.27. &amp; 27.26.29. Iohn. 19.34. Heb. 9.28. &amp; 1.10.</note>
               <label>A.</label> Thus: I doe ſtedfaſtly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, that Ieſus Chriſt the Sonne of God, is God and Man, and that his Body was broken, that is to ſay, whipped, ſcourged, and buffet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and crucified, and pierced with a ſpeare, and many wayes afflicted: and that his Blood guſhed out, and flowed from him, to make a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice to God, and ſatisfaction for my ſinnes: and ſo féeding upon my Lord and Saviour ſpiritually by faith, I eate and drinke his body and blood.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Then doe you not thinke that in this Bread and Wine there is preſent the very naturall Bodie
<pb facs="tcp:27070:5"/>
and Blood of Chriſt, as hée was borne of the Virgin <hi>Mary?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> No. God forbid. For his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall Body is now aſcended up into Heaven, and is glorified,<note place="margin">Acts 1.9.</note> and <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>itteth at the right hand of GOD the Father,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 7.55. Epheſ. 1.10. Coloſ. 3. Acts 3.25.</note> and from thence hée <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hall not come till the end of the world.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Is not Chriſt then preſent in the Sacrament?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Yes: Hee is truly and indeed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented unto our ſaith. For the breaking of the Bread ſignifieth his tormented body, and the powring out of the Wine, the ſhedding of his moſt precious Blood.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.16.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Then me thinks there is a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwéene our common bread and wine which wee receive for our daily ſuſtenance, and this Bread and Wine?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> No doubt there is.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> What is that?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> The Bread and Wine which wée commonly receive, doe nothing differ from theſe in ſubſtance, but onely in the uſe and end.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:27070:6"/>
               <label>Q.</label> How ſo?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> For theſe wee take and uſe, to the end that our bodies onely may bee nouriſhed: But theſe wee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, to ſignifie the great myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of our Redemption purchaſed by Ieſus Chriſt. And therefore they are called holy myſteries, becauſe they lively ſet forth and ſeale the ſame un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Doe all that receive the Bread and Wine, alſo partake the Body and Blood of Chriſt?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> No verily: For they that re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceive unworthily, eate and drinke their owne damnation, as Sain<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith.<note place="margin">Cor. 12.9.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> How then ſhall wee bee worth<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> receivers, and come to this Table a<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wée ought to come?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> If wee examine and prepare ou<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſelves.<note place="margin">Ibid verſe 28.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> How ſhall wée come prepared?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Obſerving foure things. Firſt If wée have true repentance for ou<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſinnes paſt. Secondly, If wee hav<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a lively Faith in the death of ou<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Lord Ieſus Chriſt.<note place="margin">1 Repentance. 2 Faith.</note> Thirdly, I<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:27070:6"/>
wée bée in love and charitie with all <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uen, Fourthly,<note place="margin">3 Charity. 4 Thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note> If wee bee thankfull to our Almighty Saviour, for his great goodneſſe declared in his holy Supper, as a ſure pledge of his love: In reſpect of which duty of ours, it is called the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> or Sacrament of thankſgiving.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> What is required in true Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Chiefly foure things: Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, Contrition, Faith, and purpoſe of amendment. Firſt, That wee acknowledge our ſelves ſinners. Secondly,<note place="margin">Pſal. 32.5. 1 Iohn 1.9. Ioel 2.13. 2 Cor. 7.10.</note> that wee be heartily and ſincerely ſory for our ſins. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that wee beleevee ſtedfaſtly for the merits Ieſus Chriſt, they ſhall bee forgiven. Fourthly,<note place="margin">Acts 10.13.</note> that wee fully reſolve, and purpoſe with our ſelves, never to commit them nor the like againe, but to lead the reſt of our lives according to Gods holy will and commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.<note place="margin">Mat. 3.8.11. and 4.17. Epheſ. 4.28. 2 Pet. 1.20. Heb. 10.26.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> What faith is heere required of you?</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:27070:7"/>
               <label>A.</label> A ſpeciall and peculiar faith, th<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> applyeth to my ſoule and conſcien<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the Body and Blood of Ieſus Chriſt crucified and ſhed for me as truly <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> my mouth receiveth the Bread that broken<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 6.47.48. &amp;c.</note> and the Wine that is powr<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> out.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q</label> Why is charity ſo neceſſary?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> For theſe cauſes: firſt, becauſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> our Saviour Chriſt commandeth it ſecondly,<note place="margin">Mat. 5.13.</note> becauſe if we doe not from our hearts forgive one another, n<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> more will our heavenly Father fo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>give us: thirdly, becauſe the Supper doth ſignifie unto us,<note place="margin">Mat. 61.8.5. and 18.35.</note> firſt the unſpeakeable love of Chriſt to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wards us, that gave himſelfe fo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> us.<note place="margin">Gal. 1.4.</note> Secondly, the uniting of u<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all that are Gods Children, bot<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with him our Head, and amon<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> our ſelves: And for that reaſon it i<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> called by the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 1.3. 1 Cor. 10.16.17. Ibid.</note> the Com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>munion.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Well, how ſhall we be thankfull</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> If we worſhip and ſerve God.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q</label> How ought GOD to be wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhipped?</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:27070:7"/>
               <label>A.</label> In ſpirit and truth.<note place="margin">Iohn 4.25.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> How muſt we ſerve him?</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. With all our heart, and all our <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ule, and all our minde, and all our <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>trength, and that not ſo much for <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>are as for love.<note place="margin">Deut. 6.5. Mat. 22.27. Luke 1.74. Rom. 8.15.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Are we able of our ſelves to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rme theſe things?</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. No truly: But onely by the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rée Grace of GOD in Ieſus Chriſt our Lord, without whom <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee can doe nothing: for whoſe <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ke,<note place="margin">1 Iohn 15.5.</note> whatſoever is done amiſſe <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> pardoned, and whatſoever is <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eft undone, is ſupplied:<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.22.</note> For when wee have done all that we can <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oe, wee are but unprofitable ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ants.<note place="margin">Luke 17.10.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> How will you obtaine the grace <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f God?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> By true and hearty prayer in the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ame and mediation of his Sonne Ieſus Chriſt.<note place="margin">Mat. 7.7. Luke 11.9. Iohn 14.13. &amp; 16.23. Mat. 21.22. Marke 11.24. Iames. 1.6. Luke 1.81. Iames 5.16.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> How ought wee to pray that we may obtaine?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Firſt, faithfully, with an aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured truſt in GODS mercies. Secondly, fervently, with an
<pb facs="tcp:27070:8"/>
earneſt deſire and zeale to obtain<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Thirdly,<note place="margin">Rom. 12.12. Epheſ. 5.18. 2 Theſſ. 5.17.</note> continually, with godly per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeverance and importunity, neve<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> fainting till wée be heard.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> What is the beſt forme of Pra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yer?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> The ſame which is called th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Lords Prayer, becauſe the Lord him ſelfe deviſed and delivered it t<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his Diſciples in the Goſpell, ſaying When yée pray, pray thus:</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 6.4. Luke<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 11.2.</note>
               <q>Our Father which art in heaven hallowed be thy name, &amp;c.</q>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:27070:8"/>
            <head>A Prayer.</head>
            <p>ALmighty God, moſt gracious and loving Father, vouchſafe wee beſeech thee, to lighten our minds with the knowledge of thy Truth, to mollifie our hearts with the dew of thy grace, to ſubdue our affections to the obedience of thy heavenly will: Forgiving our ſinnes, and making us thankfull for all thy benefits, that we may live and dye in thy faith, feare, &amp; love, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord and onely Saviour, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Laus Deo ſemper.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
